All right, let me say
a few words about the literature.
First of all, the literature
is only meant as a supplement.
In principle, you should be able
to master the material of the lecture
and the exercises without additional books.
However, sometimes an extra book still helps.
Sometimes the literature presents the material
from a slightly different perspective than
the lecture, and that can
sometimes provide a nice additional approach.
O.k., here we first have a book
that is a very comprehensive book about UML.
Yes, UML is a modeling
method, a modeling language, which
will be maybe about 50 percent
of the lecture, if I estimate that correctly.
Maybe a little bit more, actually.
So we're going to need some
UML concepts and that's why a book
on UML is not wrong, of course.
This is a book from which I
have taken some examples into the lecture.
So if you get this book, for
example, from the library or otherwise, and
browse through it, you might
recognize some of the examples
that I have in the
lecture. In that respect, it's
actually quite suitable, the
book. Unfortunately, in the description,
even when it comes to formal things,
this book is sometimes not quite clean.
There are certain inconsistencies, and thereby,
partly also deviations from the lecture,
where I tried to
present things very uniformly.
But just as an introduction,
and especially for examples, this
book is definitely very good.
Okay, then there is another English-language
book, which is very
specific to object-oriented design,
which will also be a part of the
lecture. That's this book here, you can find
that through the library as well.
That also contains a nice motivation and
examples, some of which also
show up in the lecture.
But it's not really
a modeling book otherwise.
You can see that in the
title: it says something about implementation.
This is a book that
certainly contains some modeling parts,
in view of object-oriented design, but it
is perhaps a bit more relevant later,
especially when you
attend, for example, the lecture
Advanced Programming Techniques. So there,
to my knowledge, the book is
not used as a textbook, but
certain things, the topics that you're going
to cover there, also appear in this
book. So if you plan to listen to
that later as well, maybe that would be
a good book, which bridges from modeling to
the Advanced Programming Techniques
course, which you would probably
attend with Professor Pauli.
O.K., another book, very general,
you also see UML in the title.
Software Engineering, it's about the application of
UML in the area of modeling software.
Things are covered rather non-formally in detail,
so less formal than I'm sure
I'll do in lecture, but also not
unsuitable as an introduction and overview. What's
also particularly nice about this book is
that you wouldn't have to buy
this or get it from the library.
You can also read this electronically, and in
fact, if you're logged into the university, so
you're logged into the uniaccount, you can
also read this book electronically through this link
here. That should still work. If
necessary, if you are not in the
University network, you have to access it via
VPN. Maybe this VPN access has already been explained
to you, or you have already used this
in the last semesters, if you are not
in the first year.
Okay, another book on UML.
Although UML doesn't completely make up
the lecture, we'll see other books in
a moment, but here's another
book on UML. It's very comprehensive,
with only excerpts relevant to
us. Interesting perhaps for
you because it is also available in English.
Here you can see the German book, but
for the English-speaking students, this book is also
available in English and as far as I know,
it is also available in our
library. So at least the original can
be borrowed there. Well,
then I had already
said, the course will not only be
about UML. Another important modeling tool
that we will use in the
lecture is the so-called Petri nets.
While you may already know UML,
at least class diagrams, from school classes,
Petri nets are probably most familiar
to you if you have taken the
computer science prerequisite course or if you
have attended other lectures as
ISE students where Petri nets were also used.
There are several books on that as well, again
there's a book available online.
If you're logged into the Uniaccount,
here's a paper on Petri
nets, which is very example driven.
So it's less formal, but contains many
examples that will be useful to us.
Then, a little bit in contrast, I've
cited a book here that is very formal.
So, this deals with more
formal aspects of Petri nets.
Again, that fits in with the lecture
as far as what we're going to do.
We're not going to cover everything that's in this book,
but some more formal concepts that we're going to explore
regarding Petri nets, you might find
in this book rather than the book shown before.
And also this book should
be available to you electronically
if you access it through the Uni account.
Okay, let's discuss something in English once more.
The two books just now were
German books. For the English-speaking
students, but also for others,
this article might be interesting.
It is in English and has
a slightly different style than the books.
The books are textbooks, but this
is a review article that was
written quite a while ago.
It also contains good motivation, examples,
and also discusses some of the
formal properties we will be looking at.
You see this up here, Properties,
Analysis and Applications, so both examples, applications,
and the properties and analysis of Petri
nets, which is what we'll be doing.
Of course, since it's only a part of the lecture,
not in the same depth as it's approached here in
the article, but nevertheless, that's also a
possible approach to this part of the lecture.
OK, in a similar vein, also
as a scholarly article rather than
a textbook, here is an article by Harel.
That should also be available to you, and
even without the restriction of having to
be logged in from the Uniaccount.
Why is this article relevant? Because
it lays the foundation for a
part of UML, namely UML state diagrams. This
will be the last chapter in the lecture
where we deal with this
particular type of statecharts or
state diagrams in UML. This is
often perceived as the most complex
part of the lecture.
UML statecharts are also
explained to some extent in UML books.
But in a very nice and intuitive way,
in my opinion, they are just described in
the original article that formed the basis for
UML state diagrams later. The
syntax is not one hundred percent
exactly the same there, but the important concepts
we will be looking at from statecharts, you
will find well explained in English in that article.
Okay, I think I have one more book ready.
Exactly, this is the book, also
available in English in the library.
To my knowledge not electronically,
but as a hard copy.
Again, a very comprehensive book
that covers a lot on UML.
In particular, that's why I still
included it here, it also covers the
dynamic aspects, dynamic modeling with UML, which doesn't
necessarily happen to the same extent in all of
the UML references that I mentioned before.
Yes, we will look
at static and dynamic modeling.
Static modeling with UML is explained
very well in very many
places. Also, simply in introductory books
on software engineering, the dynamic
aspects, which include statecharts,
which are certainly more difficult and are
not covered everywhere in the same way,
are articulated in this book
just so. Okay, again to repeat: You
don't have to read any of these books.
You don't have to pick up any of
these books at all if you don't like
to do so. But it might be helpful if you need
more examples, want to read something
again in a different way than
I explain it in the lecture, or just
want to have more practice material as well.